本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
ルシタニアに協力する者がいるとすれば　それは奴隷たちだ
If there are any who would aid Lusitania,
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
they are the slaves.
"Aid us, and we will reward
you with freedom and wealth."
我々に協力すれば　自由と財産を与える…
そうルシタニア軍が呼びかければ　どうだろう
What if the Lusitanian army
were to say that to them?
Some among the slaves
would surely rise up in rebellion.
奴隷たちの中には　反乱を起こす者も出てくるでしょうね
エクバターナの奴隷の数は　貴族や神官よりも多い
The slaves in Ecbatana
outnumber the nobles and priests.
It would be bad.
まずいな
It is exactly as Your Highness has surmised.
殿下のお考えのとおりです
If the slaves were to all rise up in revolt,
奴隷たちが一斉に反旗を翻せば
even the impregnable Ecbatana
is unlikely to last for long.
堅牢なエクバターナといえど　長くはもちますまい
ならば　早くエクバターナへ行かねば
Then, we must hurry to Ecbatana!
Please resist that urge, Your Highness.
抑えてください　殿下
With only the four of us, we do not
have the power to save Ecbatana.
我々４人だけでは　エクバターナを救う力にはなりえません
Before such a thing could come to pass,
このようなことになる前に
your lord father should have freed the slaves.
父王陛下は奴隷を解放するべきだったのです
Rise up, slaves!
立ち上がれ　奴隷たち
お前たちを縛り搾取するパルスに
How long will you bow your heads to Pars,
いつまで頭を垂れているのか
who chain you and misuse you?!
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Garshasph"
Sām"
圧政者を打倒せよ
Overhrow your oppressors!
These aren't my words
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
If the whole world only had left hands
时间轴
电池雪糕
压制
Coolkid
Don't be the bastards who hide their right hands
There's nothing beyond this azure
The day I realized that,
I stopped looking up at the sky
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You'd end up breathing in the bad stuff, too
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You are friend, Baby Dream
Before I knew it, my heart
Was full of things I had to love all the way
Always losing, leaving
Even the unbearable stuff
Because I don't want to live my days
lamenting, unable to keep them safe
You are friend, Baby, Dream
I'll grow even stronger
These aren't my words
But our words
Lord Marzbān Garshasph!
マルズバーン・ガルシャースフ様
あれを…
There...
Curse you, Lusitania!
おのれ　ルシタニアめ
Marzbān Manūchurh... Marzbān Khayr...
マルズバーン・マヌーチュルフ
マルズバーン・ハイル
Lord Erān Vahriz!
エーラーン・ヴァフリーズ殿…
Surely not... His Majesty as well?
まさか　陛下も
No, my lady. From what we saw,
いえ　見たところ　陛下の御首級はさらされておりませぬ
His Majesty's head was
not among those exposed.
My Lady Queen...
王妃様
You did well to report this to me.
報告　ご苦労さまでした
You may go.
下がってよいですよ
Yes, my lady.
ははっ
The Lady Queen did
not ask after Prince Arslan...
王妃様はアルスラーン殿下のことはお聞きにならぬのだな
それだけ気が動転しておられるのだろう
It shows just how troubled she must be.
サームよ　やはり城門を開いて打って出るべきだ
Sām, I still believe we should
open the gates and launch an attack.
What else is our cavalry good for?
なんのための騎兵だ
Patience.
焦るな
If we wait for reinforcements
from Peshawar on our eastern border
東方国境ペシャワールからの援軍を待って挟み撃ちにすれば
and attack them from both sides,
we will suffer fewer losses
and settle this once and for all.
損害も少なく　勝負はつく
But...
しかし…
Slaves!
奴隷たち
How long will you bow your heads to Pars,
お前たちを縛り搾取するパルスに
who chain you and misuse you?!
いつまで頭を垂れているのか
Defend your dignity!
Sever those chains and rise up!
己の尊厳を守るために
鎖を断ち切って立て
Darn it!
Rise up, slaves!
散れ　敵の妄言など聞くな
Break it up! Do not listen
to the enemy's drivel!
Garshasph, stop that!
ガルシャースフ　やめろ
We mustn't use force to control them!
力ずくで押さえつけてはいかん
やはり速戦即決だ　サーム
Decisive action and a
quick resolution is still best, Sam.
Hey...
奴隷どもめ　いつ何をやらかすか分かったものではない
Those damn slaves.
There is no knowing when
they might get up to no good.
Do not be hasty.
慌てるな　今は援軍を待て
Right now, wait for reinforcements.
When will those reinforcements arrive?!
援軍など　いつ来る
After receiving news of defeat at Atropatene,
アトロパテネの敗報から　兵を整え
they must muster the troops,
and assuming they race night
and day all the way here,
遠路昼夜駆け続けたとして　何日かかる
how many days would that take?!
Lord Marzbāns Sām and Garshasph!
マルズバーン・サーム様　ガルシャースフ様
The slaves have set fire to the Great Temple!
奴隷どもが大神殿に火を放ちました
What?!
何
Not only that, but they are
trying to open the western gates!
しかもヤツら西の城門を開けようとしています
So, they mean to invite the Lustanian army in!
ルシタニア軍を呼び込むつもりか
奴隷たちの不満は想像していた以上に根深い
The malcontent among the slaves
runs deeper than I had imagined.
Open the gates!
門を開けろ
Freedom! Freedom will be ours!
自由だ　自由を手に入れるんだ
Guard the gates with your lives!
Do not let them open it!
城門を死守しろ　開けさせるな
どけ　貴様ら
Move aside, you bastards!
卑しいヤツらめ
You damned degenerates!
Any who approaches this gate
will get his head knocked off!
門に近づく者は首をたたき落とすぞ
It hurts...
痛ぇよ
Garshasph! Do you feel proud killing slaves?!
ガルシャースフ　奴隷を殺して自慢になるのか
ヤツらは奴隷ではない　謀反人だ
They are not slaves! They are rebels!
Who only have sticks?!
棒切れしか持たぬ者をか
They held swords in their hearts!
心に剣を持っておったわ
Look at them, Garshasph.
見ろ　ガルシャースフ
You killed ten rebels,
お主は　１０人の謀反人を殺したが
but instead, you will give
rise to a thousand more rebels.
代わりに　１０００人の謀反人を生むことになるぞ
It's the north gate this time!
今度は北門だ　奴隷たちがまた蜂起したぞ
There's another slave revolt!
奴隷どもめ　毎日毎日何考えてやがるんだ
Those damn slaves. What the
hell are they thinking all day long?
We should just throw them all in jail!
みんな牢屋にぶち込んじまえばいいんだ
But then, no work would get done.
それでは仕事が回らんだろ
ヤツらは危険だ
They are dangerous.
It is no longer possible
to suppress the slaves using force.
もはや　奴隷たちを力で押さえつけることは不可能です
Why is that? The slaves do
not even have proper weapons.
なぜですか　奴隷はまともな武器も持たぬのに
反乱を起こす者の数があまりにも多すぎるのです
Those who are rising up in
rebellion are far too numerous.
In order to resolve the current situation,
現状を打開するには　彼らの不満を和らげるしかありません
our only choice is to
alleviate their dissatisfaction.
To that end,
そのために　奴隷に多少の恩賞を与え　待遇を改善するとの
I would ask that you issue
a proclamation that the slaves
will be rewarded with a modest sum
and that they will be treated better.
布告を出していただきたいのです
If I were to do such a thing,
そんなことをすれば　パルスの社会制度が揺らぎます
it would shake the
foundations of Parsian society.
敵はその社会制度そのものを利用してきているのです
The enemy is using those
very foundations against us!
We have not a moment to lose right now!
今や一刻の猶予もありません
考えておきましょう
I shall think on it.
I am most grateful.
恐れ入ります
Things are starting to
look worse and worse now.
いよいよ　雲行きが怪しくなってきたか
Perhaps I had better take my leave soon.
そろそろ　おいとました方がよさそうかな
Master Gieve, the Grand Vizier,
Lord Husrab, would like to see you.
ギーヴ様　宰相のフスラブ様がお呼びです
By my eye, not only do you excel with the bow,
そなた　弓だけではなく　才知も優れておるとみたが
but you are sharp-witted as well.
What say you?
どうかな
I have been told that time and
time again, ever since I was a child,
子供の頃から　さんざん　そう言われておりました　宰相閣下
Your Excellency.
Th-Then, trusting in that sharp wit of yours...
"Grand Vizier, Kingdom of Pars
Husrab"
で…では　その才知を見込んでのことなのじゃが
Will you not do something for me?
ひとつ頼まれてくれぬか
I sense swords and armor
behind the hanging screen.
幕の後ろに　剣と甲冑の気配
How bothersome.
面倒だな
Well?
どうじゃ
For a justifiable cause and reward,
正当な理由と報酬　それと成功の可能性があれば
and if there is a chance
of success, I will accept.
お引き受けします
The cause is the continued
survival of the Kingdom of Pars.
理由は　パルス王国の存続　ひとえにそのためじゃ
That and nothing else.
You will be rewarded generously.
報酬は存分に遣わそう
お主には　秘密の通路を通り
I want you to take a secret passage
王妃様を城外の安全な場所へ　お連れしてもらいたいのだ
to escort the Lady Queen to
a safe place outside the castle.
It is slippery here. Please watch your step.
足元が滑ります　お気をつけて
No king in residence.
王もおらぬ
And now, no queen in residence.
王妃もおらぬで　何が王都だ
Royal Capital, my ass.
And abandoning the one million
people of Ecbatana to boot.
しかも　エクバターナ１００万の民を捨て置くとは
Good grief.
やれやれ　どこぞにまともな王はおらんもんかねぇ
Is there no decent king to be had anywhere?
How long do you plan to remain here?
いつまでここにとどまっているつもりだ
やはり　エクバターナに向かうべきでは…
Perhaps we should head for Ecbatana, after all?
Must I lecture you on strategy as well?
お前にも戦術の講義が必要か
No matter how superb a fighter you may be,
いかにお前が優れた兵といえど
one man on a horse cannot
win against the Lusitanian army.
単騎でルシタニア軍に勝つことなど　できん
If we can meet up with
the men stationed in Ecbatana...
エクバターナの兵と合流できれば…
無理だな
Impossible.
敵は奴隷とルシタニア軍　合わせて数十万だ
The enemy, slaves and
the Lusitanian army combined,
number several hundred thousand.
With only the soldiers left within
the walls, we would have too few.
城内に残った兵だけでは　数が少なすぎる
You would knowingly expose
His Highness to danger?
みすみす　殿下を危険にさらすつもりか
However...
しかし
While we may not be able
to win against the army,
軍に勝つことはできずとも
we can surely bring down a commander.
将を討つことはできよう
どういう意味だ
What do you mean by that?
Right now, the opponent that we should take on
今　我々が相手取るべきは　ルシタニア軍全体ではない
is not the whole of the Lusitanian army.
It is Kharlan.
カーラーンだ
At the moment, he is likely
fully occupied with sieging Ecbatana.
今のところ　ヤツはエクバターナの攻城に掛かりきりだろう
But after that, he is certain
to come after His Highness.
だが　そのあとは　必ず殿下を狙って動く
And with relatively few men.
それも　比較的少数でな
How can you know that?
なぜ分かる
He is originally a commanding officer of Pars.
ヤツはもともとパルスの将だ
ルシタニア兵から多くの信頼を得ているとは思えん
It is doubtful that he has the
trust of many Lusitanian soldiers.
Our time to fight will come
我々の勝負どきは
カーラーンがルシタニア軍の中から突出して動いたときだ
when Kharlan makes his move
apart from the Lusitanian army.
Capturing him will not only allow us
to reduce the enemy's strength,
ヤツを捕らえれば　敵の戦力を削れるうえに
but also, to learn of the
circumstances behind his actions.
裏の事情を知ることができる
Useful for us in considering
our strategy going forward, no?
今後の戦略を考えるうえで　有効だろう
カーラーンが動くまで　黙って待っていろというのか
So, you are telling us to stay quiet
and wait until Kharlan makes his move.
Controlling your emotions for
the greater good can be a necessity.
大局のために　感情を抑えることも必要だ
I have returned.
ただいま戻りました
Good of you to go out there.
How is the situation?
ご苦労　状況は
山中の追っ手たちに変化はありません
There is no change among
those pursuing us in the mountains.
相変わらず包囲網を中心に　闇雲に我々を捜しているようです
As ever, they seem focused
on keeping us encircled
as they haphazardly search for us.
まだ　カーラーンはエクバターナから動いてはいないようだな
It seems Kharlan has yet to leave Ecbatana.
You must be tired.
疲れたでしょう　少し休みますか
Shall we rest for a while?
無理しない方がいい
Better not strain yourself.
Just having to behave as though
you are the Lady Queen is hard enough.
王妃様の振る舞いをするだけでも　大変なのだから
How did you know?
なぜ分かったのです
By smell.
匂いで
あんたと王妃様では　肌の匂いが違う
Your skin smells different
from that of the Lady Queen.
Even when using the same perfume.
同じ香水を使ってもな
You serve as the body double,
while the deceitful Lady Queen escapes.
あんたが身代わりになって
その間に　うそつきの王妃様を逃がす
そういう段取りだろ
That is the plan, right?
That is the way of the aristocracy.
身分の高い人とは　そういうものだ
他人が自分のために奉仕し　犠牲になるのは当然と思っている
They take it for granted
that others will serve them
and be sacrificed for their sakes.
How fine for them.
いい気なもんさ
I will not permit you to cast
aspersions upon the Lady Queen!
王妃様を誹謗するのは許しませぬぞ
Well, well.
おやおや
No matter what the Lady Queen
or the Lord Grand Vizier may be thinking,
王妃様や宰相様のお考えがどうであろうと
my sole concern is to fulfill my duty.
私は自分の役目を果たすだけのこと
そういうのを奴隷根性というのさ
That sort of attitude
is called the servile spirit.
Then, are you saying that
you cannot take me any farther?
ならば　これ以上　私を連れて先へは行けぬと
俺が引き受けたのは王妃の護衛だ
I accepted the job of escorting the Queen.
Not escorting a lady-in-waiting
disguised as the Queen.
王妃に化けた官女の護衛じゃない
Whoa-oh.
おっと
Now, wait.
まあ　待て
Even so, you are reasonably beautiful,
それでも　お主はそこそこの美人だから
so I would not be against
delivering you to your destination.
送り届けてやらんこともないぞ…
H-Hey, now...
お…おいおい…　勝手に行くな
Do not go off on your own...
Oh-ho.
Well, now.
これはこれは
まさか　このような所で　光栄あるパルス王妃様に会おうとは
I never imagined
that I would meet the esteemed
Lady Queen of Pars in a place such as this.
You have saved me the
trouble of looking for you.
捜す手間が省けたぞ
I should say that you and that Andragoras
あのアンドラゴラスとお似合いの夫婦と言うべきだな
are a well-matched couple.
One abandoned his men and fled the battlefield.
かたや　兵を捨てて戦場を逃げ出し
And one has left her people
behind to go underground.
かたや　人民を放り出して地下へと潜る
Where has the dignity gone
of those who occupy the throne?
王座に座る者の威厳はどこへやら
What manner of man are you?
そなたは何者です
パルスに誠の正義を敷こうと志す者だ
I am one who would bring true justice to Pars.
Lord Kharlan?
カーラーン様
What are you doing here?
なぜ　このような所に…
カーラーン様だと
Lord Kharlan, you say?
You are not the Queen, are you?!
貴様　王妃ではないな
I do not need those who are of no use to me.
俺の役に立たぬ者はいらん
Curse yourself for having
chosen the wrong master to serve.
仕える主君を間違えた己を呪え
Let us go.
行くぞ
We will infiltrate the royal
palace before the night is out
今晩中に王宮に侵入し　内からかく乱する
and throw them into confusion from within.
本物の王妃もまだ城内に残っているかもしれん
The real Queen may still
be within the walls as well.
Wait.
待て
何者かは知らんが　美人を殺すとは何事だ
I do not know who you are,
but you killed a beauty.
What is the meaning of this?
生きていれば　悔い改めて俺に貢いでくれたかもしれぬのに
Had she lived, she may have grown
remorseful and rewarded me lavishly.
顔を見せたらどうだ　色男
How about you show
me your face, you charmer?
Or is it because you have mercury
instead of blood in your veins
それとも　血の代わりに水銀が流れているから　そんな素顔になったのか
that your face has come to look like that?
Are you all right?
ご無事ですか
その小うるさい蚊をたたき潰せ
Swat down that pesky mosquito!
We will be going on ahead.
我々は　先へ行く
Yes, sir!
ははっ
Well, well. How cold of you.
おやおや　つれないねぇ
Silver Mask.
銀仮面
One down to start with.
まずは１人
Wh-Why you!
お…おのれ
I have him cornered!
追い詰めた
さて…　どうする
Now, then...
What to do?
Should I go rescue the deceitful Lady Queen?
うそつきの王妃様を救いに行くか
それとも　これでさよならか
Or make my fare-thee-wells with this?
All right!
よし
混乱に紛れて　財宝の一部を頂戴しよう
I will take advantage of the confusion
and make off with some treasure.
ついでに美人もいたら頂戴しよう　そうしよう
While I am at it, if there are any beauties,
I will make off with them as well. Yes, I will!
死人には必要ないものだ
Not something the dead need.
I will appreciate every coin
as I spend them, so be grateful.
俺がありがたく使ってやるから　感謝しろよ
かなりの人数だ
There are quite a few of them.
見つかると厄介だな
It will be troublesome if they find me.
The east gate is thinly manned!
東門が手薄だ　北門から兵を回せ
Reassign men from the north gate!
ははっ
Lord Sām!
サーム様
No matter how many we bring down,
they are not easing their attack!
ヤツら　落としても落としても　攻撃の手を緩めません
They are attacking more
fiercely than usual tonight.
今夜は　いつにも増して　攻撃が激しい
Fire at the royal palace?!
王宮から火が
Impossible...
バカな…
ここは任せる
I leave matters here to you!
はっ
Yes, sir!
こいつら　どこから
Where did these bastards come from?!
What is that?
なんだ
What's going on?
どうなってる
どいてろ
Get back!
You know what to do, right?!
やることは分かってるな
Overthrow your oppressors!
圧政者を打倒しろ　行け
Go!
Send them running!
蹴散らせ
It is the blessing of Yaldabaoth!
イアルダボート神の恵みだ
Damn it! Did they come up
through the underground aqueducts?!
くそ　地下水路からか
How?!
どうして
なっ　カーラーン
Kharlan!
Kharlan, it was true that
you deserted to the enemy?!
カーラーン　寝返ったとの話は本当だったのか
Why did you betray your kingdom?!
なぜ　国を売った
Circumstances have led me to this!
You would not understand!
故あってのことよ　お主には分からぬ
No, of course not! I could never understand!
おお　当たり前だ　分かるものか
Surrender, Sām.
降伏しろ　サーム
If you convert to the Faith of Yaldabaoth,
イアルダボート教に改宗すれば　地位も命も保障してやる
I will guarantee both your life and your rank.
A dog going on about a
human's rank? You make me laugh!
犬が人間の地位を云々するなど　片腹痛い
Sām, wait!
サーム　待て
Wh-Who are...
な…何者…
Lord Garshasph! There!
ガルシャースフ様　あれを
The gate is going up!
城門が上がっていきます
What?!
何　バカな
Impossible!
The slaves, eh?
奴隷か
Guard the west gate with your lives!
西門を死守しろ
It's no use! The gate...!
ダメだ　門が…
Defend in front of the gate!
Do not allow them entry!
門の前で固めろ　侵入を許すな
Pars Era, the year 320, November.
パルス暦３２０年１１月
The Royal Capital of Ecbatana fell.
王都エクバターナ　陥落
With the fate of its monarch,
Andragoras, still unknown,
国王アンドラゴラスの生死も不明のまま
Pars was plunged into the darkness of chaos.
パルスは　混乱の闇に落ちた
One soul maneuvered in secret
behind the dark raging furor.
ある者は　暗き暴威の裏に暗躍し
One soul gazed upon the
fires of war that lit the night skies.
ある者は　夜闇を染める戦火を眺め
And yet another
また　ある者は　信じる正義のもとに歩みを急ぐ
hastened to where she would
find the justice she believed in.
As countless intentions swirled and eddied,
無数の思惑が渦巻き
the gears of fate began to turn.
運命の歯車は回りはじめた
は
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go, drifting
When a tale that is shapeless
Spreads across the moonlight
The treasure that is within you
Melts away into the wind now
Tomorrow, try to take
wing as your unvarnished self
Sometime, somewhere,
you wanted this, remember?
You can hear it, can't you?
There; that shining dream from that day
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go
Oh, 'til this dream comes to an end
If there were a proper way
to deal with a heathen queen,
異教徒の王妃を遇する道があるとすれば
it should have been none other than
the cruelest of deaths by execution.
最も残酷な刑死があるのみのはずであった
However, his vassals had assumed wrong.
だが　彼の家臣たちの予想は外れた
次回　美女たちと野獣たち
Next time, "The Beauties and the Beasts."
"Chapter VII
The Beauties and the Beasts"
And thus, the boy would become king.
"Chapter VII
The Beauties and the Beasts"
少年は　そして王となる